Finding Aid for Polish Activities League (Detroit, Mich.) Records, 1923-1984
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Polish Activities League (Detroit, Mich.) records 1923-1984
Polish Activities League (Detroit, Mich.)
1 microfilm roll
4 oversize volumes
6 linear feet
Detroit social service organization established to aid the Detroit Polish community. Scrapbooks, printed histories, scattered correspondence, photographs, and minute book, 1949-1954. Much of the record group is in Polish.
85139 Bd 2; BD Oversize
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was the gift of the League (donor no. 6934 ) and came to the library in 1983-1984.
The record group is open for research.
The Detroit Polish Activities League has a history extending back to 1915 when, in response to the First World War, the Detroit Polish Women's Relief Committee was formed. The Committee coordinated the activities of already existing Polish women's charitable organizations on behalf of war victims in Poland.
After the War, the Committee turned its attention closer to home. It decided to become a permanent social service agency, serving the needs of Polish families and individuals in metropolitan Detroit. Thus the group affiliated with the League of Catholic Women, changed its name to the Committee for Polish Affairs, and set up headquarters in the League's St. Anne's Community House.
Having gained experience and confidence under the aegis of the League of Catholic Women, the Committee nevertheless felt the need to move beyond the scope of Catholic charities. Accordingly, in 1924 the Committee became the Polish Activities League and opened St. Elizabeth's Community House to serve as its new headquarters.
The Polish Activities League (PAL) aimed at helping Polish immigrants adjust to their new lives without resorting to hasty, and in PAL's judgment, ill-advised, attempts at "Americanization." Instead, PAL offered a wide variety of social services intended to bolster, not erode, Polish ethnicity, especially in language and religion. Some of these services included care for Polish veterans, monetary aid to indigent Poles, and the seeking out of immigrants, especially girls and young women, in order to help them find employment. PAL also counseled families with marital problems and cooperated with the courts in helping juvenile delinquents. PAL taught courses in English, citizenship, and organized numerous clubs in the Community Houses.
PAL was originally a women's organization, but a men's division was formed in 1928. Around the same time PAL opened a summer camp for children (St. Mary's) and began publishing a monthly bilingual magazine for women, that unfortunately did not survive the Depression. In 1932 PAL opened a Relief Restaurant and a Polish Veteran's Home.
Germany's invasion of Poland in 1939 focused PAL's attention overseas once more. The organization sent food, clothing and money to Poland. In addition, they sent three petitions to President Roosevelt protesting Nazi atrocities. After Pearl Harbor, PAL not only supported the U.S. War effort, but also began to train social workers for rehabilitation work in Poland. The emergence of a communist government in Poland ended this plan, however.
After the war PAL began a weekly series of radio broadcasts in Polish and opened St. Mary's Home for the Aged (subsequently moved to Livonia) and bought St. Anne's Community House from the League of Catholic Women. As the old neighborhoods began to change, however, PAL found a diminishing clientele for its services. In 1956 PAL was put under the jurisdiction of the Catholic Youth Organization, and with this protection managed to survive, although St. Anne's Community House was forced to close in 1973.
The records of the Polish Activities League (PAL) comprise six linear feet with an additional four oversize volumes and one financial ledger on microfilm. The record group is organized into the following series: Background Information, Organizational Files, Scrapbooks, and Photographs. Much of the record group is in Polish.
Subjects:
Detroit (Mich.)--Social life and customs--1921-1930.; Detroit (Mich.)--Social life and customs--1931-1940.; Detroit (Mich.)--Social life and customs--1941-1950.; Detroit (Mich.)--Social life and customs--1951-1960.; Detroit (Mich.)--Social life and customs--1961-1970.; Detroit (Mich.)--Social life and customs--1971-1980.; Polish Activities League (Detroit, Mich.); Polish Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Women--Michigan--Detroit--Societies and clubs.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Camps--Michigan--Memphis.; Camp St. Mary's (Memphis, Mich.); Catholic Church--Michigan.; Pageants.; Polish Activities League (Detroit, Mich.); Polish Americans--Clothing and dress.; Polish Americans--Organizations.; Polish Americans--Social life and customs.; Religious services.; Shrines.; St. Ann's Community House (Detroit, Mich.); St. Elizabeth's Community House (Detroit, Mich.)
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Background Information
  The first series, Background Information, contains several commemorative booklets from PAL's 25th, 30th, 40th and 50th Anniversaries. There is also a brief history in Polish, and a copy of PAL's Constitution.
  - History and Constitution (Box 1)
- Organizational Files
  The Organizational Files series includes extensive information on the activities and programs of PAL, other organization with whom PAL associated, correspondence, financial information, publications and public relations material, various reports (both of individual cases handled by PAL and from various PAL classes and clubs), and personal material belonging to Miss Clara Swieczkowska. She was one of the cofounders of the original Women's Relief Committee, and president of PAL from 1925 to 1935. After vacating the office of president, Swieczkowska became the general executive secretary of PAL, a position she held until 1946.
  A large portion of the Organizational Files series concerns PAL's summer camp program. These files include staff applications, "camperships-" for needy children, correspondence relating to the camps, materials on day camps and a large run of notebooks, roughly from 1949 to 1972. These chronicle the day-to-day activities of the camps, both summer and day, and frequently give counselor's evaluations of the campers and daily expenditures. There is material from three PAL camps, Resurrection, St. Mary's, and Transfiguration. (St. Mary's was the only sleep-over camp).
  - Activities and Events
    - General 1941-1959 (Box 1)
    - Mother of the Year 1968-1982 (Box 1)
    - Sweetheart of the Year 1968-1984 (Box 1)
    - Fiftieth anniversary 1974, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Associated Organizations Council of Social Agencies 1949-1950
    - Detroit Federation of Settlements 1947-1962 (Box 1)
    - Polish National Welfare Association
      - General 1935-1939 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence 1937-1939 (Box 1)
  - Clippings
    - General
      - Undated (Box 1)
      - circa 1950 (Box 1)
      - circa 1970 (Box 1)
    - Poland circa 1940 (Box 1)
  - Community Centers (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1951-1952 (Box 1)
    - 1953 (Box 1)
    - 1954 (Box 1)
    - 1955 (Box 1)
    - 1956-1957 (Box 1)
    - 1965-1972 (Box 1)
  - Finances
    - General 1944-1977 (Box 1)
      (scattered dates)
    - Ledger 1949-1954 (Box 1)
    - Ledger 1940-1949, 1 volume on 1 microfilm reel (Reel 1)
      [In microfilm cabinet]
  - Lists, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Publications
    - Liga Spraw Polskich
      - 1925-1939 (Box 2)
      - 1940-1943 (Box 2)
      - 1944-1946 (Box 2)
      - 1947-1949 (Box 2)
      - 1957-1960 (Box 2)
      - 1962-1964 (Box 2)
      - 1965-1975 (Box 2)
    - The Messenger 1940-1958 (Box 2)
  - Publicity
    - General 1954-1957 (Box 2)
    - Radio scripts
      - 1950-1951 (Box 2)
      - 1953-1954 (Box 2)
      - 1955-1956 (Box 2)
  - Reports
    - Cases (Box 2)
    - Class and club 1950 (Box 2)
    - Groupworkers
      - 1954-1955 (Box 2)
      - 1956 (Box 2)
      - 1966 (Box 2)
      - 1967 (Box 2)
      - Miscellanea (Box 2)
    - Polish (language) 1954 (Box 2)
    - Secretaries
      - 1952 (Box 2)
      - 1955 (Box 2)
      - 1956-1957 (Box 2)
    - Miscellanea (Box 2)
  - Summer Camps
    - Applications, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - "Camperships" (Box 3)
    - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Day Camps (Box 3)
    - Notebooks
      - Undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1949-1955 (Box 3)
      - 1956 (Box 3)
      - 1957-1958 (Box 3)
      - 1959, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1960 (Box 3)
      - 1961 (Box 3)
    - Resurrection Camp 1959 (Box 3)
    - St. Mary's Camp
      - 1954-1955 (clippings) (Box 3)
      - 1956 (Box 3)
      - 1959 (Box 3)
      - 1965-1972 (Box 3)
    - Transfiguration Camp (Box 3)
    - United Community Services (Box 3)
    - Miscellanea (Box 3)
  - Speeches 1969-1982 (Box 3)
  - Printed Material (Box 3)
  - Special Interests
    - Immigration, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - School Records, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Senior Citizens
      - Clippings (Box 4)
      - Collected Materials (Box 4)
      - Kundig Center (Box 4)
      - Miscellanea (Box 4)
    - Volunteers (Box 4)
  - Swieczkowska, Clara-Personal, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Miscellanea (Box 4)
- Scrapbooks
  Scrapbooks is the largest series in the record group. These volumes consist almost entirely of newspaper clippings, three-quarters of which are in Polish. The scrapbooks span the years 1923-1968.
  - 1923-1927 (Volume 1)
  - 1927-1932 (Volume 2)
  - 1933-1937 (Box 4)
  - 1937-1941 (Box 4)
  - 1940-1949 (Box 4)
  - 1943-1946 (Box 4)
  - 1944-1946 (Box 5)
  - 1946-1948 (Box 5)
  - 1948 (Box 5)
  - 1949, 2 volumes (Box 5)
  - 1951-1952 (Box 5)
  - 1953 (Volume 3)
  - 1954-1955 (Volume 4)
  - 1957-1958 (Box 5)
  - 1958 (Box 5)
  - 1959-1960 (Box 5)
  - 1959-1961 (Box 6)
  - 1961-1962 (Box 6)
  - 1962 (Box 6)
  - 1965-1967 (Box 6)
  - 1968 (Box 6)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series dates from ca. 1925 to 1970 and includes photos of pageants, and shrines, and views of people and activities at Camp St. Mary's and at St. Elizabeth's and St. Ann's community houses.
  - AIDE training program, Duquesne University (Box 6)
  - Camp St. Mary's, Memphis, Michigan, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Churches and Clergy (Box 6)
  - Groups (Box 6)
  - Lay Leaders (Box 6)
    (see also Clara Swieczkowska)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Pageants (Box 6)
  - St. Elizabeth's Community House, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - St. Elizabeth's and St. Ann's
    - Activities (Box 6)
    - Groups (Box 6)
  - Shrines (Box 6)
  - Swieczkowska, Clara (Box 6)